[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software become an autonomous digital
Enterprise and your business can achieve
aame status intelligent predictive
systems effortless Automation and
technology and people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
Enterprise visit bmc.com aame for more
information this is Priyanka Ragan for
software engineering radio and today
we're going to be talking about software
bugs and why it's okay to ship your
software with bugs and and my guest for
today is James Smith who is the CEO and
co-founder of bugsnag and James is um an
entrepreneur he's also a software
engineer and he has a broad base of
experience he's U very passionate about
building great products growing teams
and scaling infrastructure with data and
he's also developed many U you know open
source projects like uh loopj which is
used by companies such as Twitter
Pinterest and Trello so so welcome to
the show James thank you for having me
pranka so let's Jump Right In we want to
talk about you know bugs so in our
industry is you know you know we've
moved from many different software
processes like you know going from back
in the day waterfall to you know now
where we are agile and then we have all
these sort of you know continuous
integration processes like you know we
have devops Dev SEC Ops bis devops all
of these things with the intent of you
know reducing bugs before you ship the
software so we're curious to know why
you think it's okay to ship software
with bugs yeah so I think to be clear I
think it's a really really good idea to
reduce bugs before you ship your
software as much as possible M
especially when it comes to best
practices like uh just adding linting
and having cicd run your tests and
builds every single time right but uh
the reality is that that it's a tradeoff
if you want to be competitive delivering
your features or your product to your
customer base uh you have to figure out
well would it be more valuable to
deliver those features to my customers
quicker and so one part of this question
is will uh reducing the time that we
spend on the human powered QA or uh test
coverage or code coverage uh get us to
Market quicker but in reality
I actually think the big reason why it's
okay to have bugs slip through the
production is because there's really
nothing you can do about it and so even
if you have the absolute best most
locked down 100% code coverage linting
and you run your test every time you
write type a character on the keyboard
in reality you cannot test every single
experience that your customers are going
to have right this is particularly true
in in the clientside mobile browser
environments where you know there's
there's tens of thousands of different
Android phones on the market right and
you're not going to be able to run your
software on every single device with
every piece of data coming through every
flow in your software so it's more of a
reality I think that you can reduce the
egregious bugs and the worst case bugs
but some will absolutely slip through
and then sometimes it's okay sometimes
it's okay to have bugs slip through the
production so that you can get that
feature out to Market quicker one really
good example of that if I remember
rightly when a few years ago Lyft and
Uber were both working on their shared
rides experience so before this launched
you had to ride on your own in a lift or
an Uber and it used to be called was
Uber pool and lift liner used to be
called and um it turns out that they
were both working on it in parallel and
Uber launched theirs before Lyft
launched theirs and then Lyft went out
and launched it the day after or within
a week of uber having their feature
launched and Uber got all the Press Uber
got all of the excitement about it all
the buzz about it um but were like damn
it we we were ready we were right there
we've been building it uh you know
obviously they different features
different experiences but um you know
sometimes it's okay to to trade these
things off right I mean yeah because you
have to get to Market quicker so yeah um
okay so that's so so in so you're saying
it's good to do a lot of this you know
static code analysis unit testing
whatever your early load and security
testing all that is good but uh you know
you can't be perfect uh is that would
that be right if if I were to sum it up
that's right yeah and I also I'm I'm
oversimplifying here because there are
environments like you're not if you're
building a space shuttle or medical
software you know situations where
you're going to get in big trouble
people might die or or or billions of
dollars might get lost if you if you
don't catch that bug you want to be a
lot more careful about this and take a
different approach but if you're doing
web software that you're delivering on a
regular basis so you can hot fix and
Patch right or even apps delivered on a
phone or or desktop that you can update
you know yes you can a little bit more
uh you you can get away with a lot more
okay but like I was also curious in your
experience you know there are these
certain types of bugs which are sort of
you know uh you primarily come from you
know say developer being a little lazy
and you know uh you not doing enough
checking and those kind of things what
are your uh you know what's your take on
that I mean I guess a lot of these kind
of you know early testing helps with
that right yeah the it really depends on
the language that you're working with
it's actually a really big variant on
this between languages there's modern
languages like um like Swift that that
try to force you to not use uh
uninitialized variables and this is a
really common cause of problems in in
other languages like JavaScript or right
or Ruby even uh or or or Java and I
think that I would argue that it's
probably not de I know what you mean
though it's not developer laziness I
think it's more lack of care or lack of
understanding I think that you'll see
that the junior developers people who've
been in their career for only a couple
of years are going to be the ones
racking up the null pointer exceptions
and uh uninitialized variables right but
there are ways around this and I feel
like the engineering organizations it's
the job of the engineering managers and
the leaders on the team to set up the
the IDE rules and the linting rules and
and the checks to to to make sure that
those those things get caught I think
most people listening will will have
done this exact same thing before and
that is
sometimes you want to just get the thing
to work because you're like right if I
just put connect this last piece of the
puzzle together I can see it doing the
thing that I want it to do and sometimes
along that Journey you want to collect
all the pipes together and you're not
going to put in all of the perfect
exception handling all the the the weird
edge cases and so that's fine as long as
you come back and and and clean it up
and make sure that you handle these
things and yeah some some languages
handle this much better than others
there's a whole wave of modern languages
that are trying to make language
features that stop
bad behavior from developers but even
outside of that uh I think in ID land
you know you can write Java code in a in
notepad if you want but most Java
developers are using some kind of IDE
and when you're using an IDE and you're
calling a function that will throw an
exception it's gonna generate that code
to make sure that you're capturing
handling that exception correctly and so
most IDs have features baked in to to
say hey heads up don't forget you need
to do this yes so you can I think it's
lack of experience lack of care maybe
getting excited about delivering these
features to your uh to your customers or
seeing it work yourself right but there
are definitely ways around it so which
actually since we're talking about
languages uh is there like do you think
there's you know uh do you see more bugs
in certain languages is there some oh
yeah absolutely um we haven't you know
what I we should do a report on this now
we have plenty of data on this we should
definitely run a report on this but I'll
just tell you off the top of my head
JavaScript 100% And there's no surprises
there JavaScript is is so easy to use
there's a lot of it's a lot of people's
first language it's uh a lot of Junior
developers will pick it up there's been
a lot of Buzz and excitement around It
On full stack and so as I said earlier
the kind of more Junior developers are
going to have more bugs but also the
language features that uh seemed like a
good idea at the time I think the the
world is moving away I by the way I love
JavaScript
I I think it's a great language bug
snags front end is actually moving from
JavaScript to typescript which is in my
mind just a way to make JavaScript more
sensible it's still JavaScript right um
but all of the the dirty things that you
can do with JavaScript get people in
trouble big time just even like
equivalence relationships and equality
relationships and casting magic casting
that's happening and I think that you
it's important for people to understand
the fundamentals of typing even in a
language like JavaScript where you know
magically typed behind the scenes but
yeah it can get you in a lot of trouble
so actually there's also this question
that you know I sort of have to ask you
know leading up to this is since you
talked about like say now you talked
about JavaScript bring something looking
at your data that it looks like
something that you know produces a lot
of bugs can I extend this question and
say is there a class of bugs coming out
of a certain type of you know
architecture or something that causes uh
more issues like you know uh certain
things are like oh no there are no bugs
in say I don't know this uh if you're
writing I don't know like some iot uh
software I don't think there's really
any sort of bugs coming in that it's not
as susceptible to say a web- based
development do you see things like that
is there some sort of analysis that that
really helps like you start a project
and you already know okay this is you
know if I'm choosing this particular
architecture and this particular design
pattern I for a fact know that I'm going
to have more bugs yeah I I feel like
that there's no I don't have any data on
this but from my experiences I can say
that the the smaller the scope of your
project and the better the contracts
between your project and other projects
the the uh the the less likely it is to
have complicated confusing bugs and so
you know this has kind of been really
highlighted by the rise of microservices
Ares right you're saying this app does
one thing and it owns this data and it
does this one thing really really well
and so when you're saying this is the
one thing that this this service does
right you can anticipate all of the
problems that that can arise a lot
easier because you're not trying to map
a whole complex State machine in your
head or whatever sure and so I'm
oversimplifying this but if you if the
more you go towards microservice land
with contracts between uh services and
applications I think the more it forces
you to document things and think about
the relationships between these
applications and think about errors that
are going to occur that could cause that
contract to break down with other
services the cont the contrary to that I
think the interactive user inter faes
tend to be the most likely to have a lot
of bugs in right because you're building
something that is going to be interacted
with by people in a lot of different
ways that maybe a lot of ways that you
don't anticipate right and also there's
a ton of asynchronous code running a lot
of your code most of your code in a UI
uh application a web app or desktop app
or mobile app is running in callbacks
you're waiting for someone to interact
with your application and callbacks can
get Gnarly sometimes you can make maybe
you were expecting some data to be
present that's not present yet at the
time someone that clicked a button or
maybe your callback javascript's really
funny because if there's an exception in
a call back it doesn't kill execution
for the rest of the application it just
causes that call back to fail so from
your customers's experience the whole
application keeps working but just your
callback your click Handler might break
and I've seen this when been you know on
a on a News website or something like
that and and try to click through to the
next article and I'm like why is
happening here so yeah I think I think
it's about well defined Concepts
ownership sure that that's what I've
seen yeah that's like yeah good design
uh would really have you have a good
bounded context and so yeah you can
reduce bogs yeah that makes a lot of
sense I I guess uh also in terms of you
know um our sort of whole UI development
there are a lot of you know third party
off the-shelf components that we use
right like uh you know any of the new uh
JavaScript frame Frameworks so whatever
like we have typescript and of course we
also have like these different um you
know angular view front end uh things
with a lot of you know third party
libraries now what happens to you know
bugs coming from your third party
libraries now that's something that
often times of course you do do um you
know you could check for vulnerabilities
and things like that you know in terms
of security but uh how do you handle
those kind of bugs any you know like the
third party that you're depending on
yeah it's it's difficult because I mean
the good news news is that most people
are using open source third party
libraries these days so you're not you
like when I started my career that
wasn't the case you you'd pay Oracle for
some SDK and you'd never be able to see
the source code for that and these days
most uh providers are making their their
third party code open source and so it's
annoying because you shouldn't have to
deal with bugs in third party code but
the reality is you will right and if
it's open source at least it gives you
the ability to go and dig into it and so
if you're using a an error uh reporting
uh an error monitoring solution like bug
snag it will show you the stack trace it
will show you the line of code uh that
caused the crash and it will show you
all of the other code paths that that um
customer went through up until the point
of the crash and so in that case you can
see hang on a second this went through
this weird file in react uh that I need
to dig into right or if the top of the
stack Trace was in the react app you're
like wait a minute it should not be
crashing inside of the react library but
I think that to avoid that you don't
lead life on the bleeding edge uh try to
try to it's very exciting to get those
hot new features uh out of your library
but don't don't immediately bump your
dependencies as soon as you know some
beta is out for a new version of react
or whatever it is I also think that
actually selection of thirdparty
libraries is a really underrated part of
software development I think sometimes
people like right I need a I don't know
what's a good example md5 I need to
generate an md5 hash so I'm just going
to go on node mpm and search for md5
hash and maybe I'll pick this one ex but
in reality you know I won't pick this
one because this uses the new promise
interface and therefore that's really
cool well is it maintained how many
stars does it have and and on on GitHub
are PLL requests and comments being
addressed and issues being addressed on
GitHub like it's actually I think people
jump to oh someone's already written
this code let me use it just like some
developers would jump to like included
jump to stack Overflow and have a look
at a snippet but in reality if you're
going to be ring on something you need
to really trust it and so doing that
research on those third party libraries
and sdks is is super critical and very
underrated and my co-founder says this
all the time he he'll say he looks for a
safe Pair of Hands uh and in third party
SDK land safe Pair of Hands might mean
the one that's been around for three
four years rather than the one that's
just been launched that's growing very
quickly we can refactor and use that
other Library if we want in future if it
becomes more stable but right now who
knows if it's even GNA exist in a year's
time right so I agree with that approach
as well right I think yeah that's uh I
think what you've said has really hit
the nail on my on my head in fact in
fact I think I also sort of just jump
and pick up the very first Library so um
I think that really is quite underrated
as you say so now that we've looked at
like you know sort of major causes of
bugs and then we've compartmentalized it
also in the sense like we've got third
party bugs and then you know because of
you know maybe uh somebody new to a
particular language causes you know
errors things like that and also we've
also looked at bugs maybe because of you
know unrealistic uh deadline we just
want to get straight out into the market
it's fine so we've got a whole you know
sort of class of bugs that we've talked
about right now let's just switch gears
a bit because I found this really
interesting article on your blog about
these worst bugs in history right and
we'll have a a link in our show notes
for our listeners but would you be able
to you know sort of give us an example
of uh something that you've researched
which you think was like oh my God I
really need to talk about this in the
show do you have anything like that like
an example that just pops out oh I mean
the wor the worst the worst one in my
mind is is the the theak 25 disaster and
this is actually I had I did a math in
computer science agree and one of the uh
the the courses I did um in computer
science was safety critical systems and
they start off not by talking about how
to work and build safety critical
designs they start off by telling horror
stories and this was one of the horror
stories and so theic 25 was this story
and incident about a radiation therapy
machine uh that was designed to treat
cancer patients so it was designed to
help people and obviously it it's not
just a a piece of Machinery it had
software in it and for whatever reason
there weren't enough safety features in
uh in the software and it led to three
people unfortunately dying and so
software bugs actually caused people to
die and it's kind of terrifying
because they were thinking about safety
criticality while building this software
uh but this was in the 80s and in the
80s this wasn't a super um well
understood space they probably weren't
teaching safety critical systems in
colleges back in the 80s and it's a it's
a really weird bug as well because it
wasn't a pure software bug it was a
multi-layered bug so they kind of rolled
out a new version of this machine and as
far as I understand it in the new
version of the machine they removed a
hardware safety feature okay and it was
intended that that Hardware safety
feature would be replaced by a software
safety feature okay so it's not like
that there was a crash or a line of code
that had the wrong variable in it or
whatever it was a design bug uh in the
the difference between the hardware team
and the software team's understanding of
how this should work obviously the this
led to the the tragedy of people dying
the the the machines were recalled by
the FDA but also looking at the other
side of things this has led to a lot of
changes in the way that we develop soft
software and I don't maybe I wouldn't
have had a safety critical course at
College if it wasn't for situations like
this right I actually ended up after
college working in as a software
consultant and one of the projects I
worked on was a high volume medical pump
okay it's for it was treatment of
patients that uh that had AIDS typically
and it was high high volume doses of of
of flu it and it's incredibly dangerous
to get that wrong if you deliver too
much of the drug that's game over for
for patients potentially and the system
that was designed that I was working on
actually it was a small box about about
the you know size of a lunch box it had
three CPUs it had a UI CPU which is the
one I was working on as a graduate
software engineer and so the worst case
scenario on that is that it could show
up something wrong on the UI which is
still really bad if you're saying that
this much fluid had been delivered but
actually under the hood less had been
delivered more delivered that's a
mismatch but the other two CPUs were
different layers of safety criticality
and so the um super Gray beard expert uh
men and women working on the project uh
for the most safety critical CPU that
had to go from multiple audits
independent uh audit and external audit
and so there's so many layers these days
of safety and as a graduate software
engineer who'd only ever worked on like
ha Web projects really before then I was
like wow this is very slow to do do
anything on this we have to send it out
for review and then then you read about
and learn about things like the the 25
and you're like yep okay this is why we
do this very important to get it right
so yeah it's a horrible story but I feel
like that I I feel like there was no
there's no malice it wasn't someone
trying to you know do do anything wrong
it was just a design problem and I think
lots of safety critical systems have
learned from that experience since then
right and design of course plays again
plays a really important part and also I
guess the one that you brought out
reviews as well right yeah yeah I think
reviews also make a sort of they are
probably underrated as well in red using
bugs I guess we can switch gears to
something a little bit lighter after
that
example I I guess for our listeners like
in the microservices world uh which is
what we are all doing right now uh
interesting to also talk about the
Facebook API bug that you had written
about uh could you tell us about how
that unfolded and you know how many
clients it affected and if I if I
remember right it was something simple
like the return type from the end point
right exactly right yeah yeah okay this
is one of these things and I you know I
understand that this is my company would
not exist if bugs didn't happen right so
bugs happen uh it's important it's
important to deal with them but like I'm
not sure if everyone's familiar with
this but if you're a a mobile developer
you probably know about this a few
months ago pretty PR much every
application that used the Facebook SDK
which is a real which is most consumer
mobile applications it turns out started
crashing some of them crashed on boot
which meant when you went to open your
Spotify application you couldn't open it
it would just crash immediately on boot
and this is on iOS and this you you
asked earlier about the third party sdks
crashing this is exactly what happened
and so anyone who'd embedded the the
Facebook SDK what was happening is the
Facebook SDK Powers things like Facebook
authentication but it also Powers things
like uh partner partner data sharing and
things like that seeing which friends
are uh listening to certain tracks and
features in in in various pieces of
software anyway the Facebook SDK goes
off and fetches data from Facebook's API
it grabs it in Json format that Json
payload comes back to the SDK and then
some Coco iOS code unpacks that Jon and
tries to do something with it now it's a
pretty common work for probably everyone
who's listening has done something like
that now obviously if the data that
comes back is not in the format you
expect you should protect against that
in fact that's exactly what you asked
about the first question pretty what are
the common bugs not protecting against
unexpected
situations that's exactly right and in
this Facebook SDK what looks like
happened was that either intentionally
or unintentionally the the team that
pass power that API that was returning
that Json payload changed the structure
of the data in that payload and okay
fine that happens right that's going to
cause a bug if you change the structure
of that data without having the new
format supported but in this case it
wasn't just the bug where some
information was missing it caused a
crash so the Coco code was expecting to
dig into a particular variable with a
particular structure so it was doing
operations on a a string that it
expected to be an array or a list I
think was the way around it worked and
so unprotected access of of the wrong
data type caused the whole piece of code
to crash and in a Coco application in
most applications that then caused the
entire application to crash because it
was an unhandled exception that bubbled
out from the SDK and then was not caught
by uh the application code and so what a
lot of the time bugs are introduced when
you change code so if you roll out a new
releas or a new version you're going to
be looking very carefully to see if
their new crashes introduced but if you
are Spotify and it's 3: in the morning
and uh Facebook pushes out and you
change to their API you do not expect
100% of your sessions to fail on iOS
which is what happened and so it's a
nightmare situation and really what you
the impact of this was huge it was
pretty much most cons most major
consumer mobile applications on iOS had
blips of outages for a number of hours
now the the impact was also kind of
insane for a product like bug snack and
so our product detects bugs crashes and
exceptions in soft in people's software
um and then gives you the data you need
to figure out what's going on and how to
fix it okay so effectively and we have a
lot of customers that are in the mobile
space and especially in the consumer
mobile space and suddenly we got a ton
tens hundreds of millions of exceptions
uh being reported to our servers so
we're again we're just our servers Auto
scale and our systems Auto scale so it
wasn't a problem but suddenly my
infrastructure team saw this big spike
coming up of all of these consumer
mobile applications on iOS uh sending
exceptions in in the fact one of the
leading exception handling providers
error monitoring providers for mobile
Google Google's offering could not cope
with the volume and in fact basically
shut down their servers for for a while
or at least stopped processing a lot of
the data so cuz effectively it's a
it's like you're getting a denial of
service right you've got all these
clients around the world sending in all
of this data at a much higher volume
than you expect so it was that was that
was bad but obviously bugs happen and
what we say uh what we say at bug sag a
lot is you know don't anger the Ops Gods
so if uh if uh some your competitor or
someone you know about software goes
down never gloat about that right never
ever gloat about that be like oh I wish
I'm glad it wasn't asked but like
because if you anger the OBS squs it'll
come back to you next
week as well but the thing that really
bugged me about this was a few weeks
later yeah the exact same bug happened
so they changed again the data format
again and the exact same bug happened so
look make a mistake learn from the
mistake yeah and I think it was was it
uh Facebook it used to say move fast and
break things was their motto uh and kind
of
kind of fine sure learn learned from
these mistakes though and the second
time it happened you know was there no
change control there who who allowed
that API change to happen that's the
thing that that I think annoyed a lot a
lot of developers because they're like
they didn't even have time between the
first incident and the second incident
to put in more uh protective code paths
to stop this from happening and and SDK
from blowing up their application right
so so actually I guess a lot also I
wonder about things like you know API
stability that you know usually have
rules for that right I mean I guess
there's generally a period of time
before you tell your clients sayy we're
changing something that's going to
really break things exactly it must have
been unintentional I think that the I
think it was a private
API uh which which maybe they they were
less careful about but it must have been
unintentional I'm sure okay but yeah
it's you know what's interesting is that
and again I don't you never know what
goes on inside of a company when there's
an outage going on right our customers
knew about this
outage seemingly hours or at least uh at
least 20 minutes before Facebook did
because one of the things our service
does it will tell you what percentage of
users and what percentage of application
sessions right are healthy or not and so
when when you're at like 99% healthy and
then sudden it goes to zero% healthy uh
it's very straightforward to see that in
in a product like bug snag um okay but
yeah all the GitHub issue uh then people
went to GitHub issues for the Facebook
SDK and started saying hey this is down
and Engineers were responding with oh
really I don't let me look into this for
you like wow who knows what was
happening but maybe they were scrambling
to get it fixed they probably were they
they probably have really good
monitoring in place but you know one
time okay second time happening right
right and I guess it also brings out how
important it is for um I guess teams to
also protect against their third party
um sdks like you say I think that's
again one area where you really need to
focus on how you you know how your
application reacts to
that become an autonomous digital
Enterprise and your business can achieve
aame status intelligent predictive
systems effortless Automation and
technology and people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
Enterprise visit bmc.com aame for more
information
okay so that's like some I I guess we've
got you know sort of a look at how bad
bugs could be you know if they happen
like you know we've got the really
serious ones that you talked about which
could be life-threatening and then of
course you've also got like you know
your day-to-day things like your
favorite app doesn't open up because of
a crash like what we just discussed I
guess now sort of logically I'd like to
move a little bit into another area of
you know software quality uh so there
was a a show in uh 2017
with SE radio I think it was episode 280
with Gerald Weinberg and he had a book I
think bugs Boo Boo and blunders and and
when he was actually talking on the show
one thing that really struck me as a
listener was um I think the anecdote
that he was giving was uh he was at you
know a car you know a car manufacturing
place where there was some sorry an auto
show I think sorry it was an auto show
and there was this new version of the
car which he was looking at and it was
great like when he was looking at the
brochures and stuff but actually when he
went into the car and you know started
driving it that's when he really felt
the car and you know found out things
about it and the an analogy was the same
thing with software you know that you
actually uh you know really know the
major issues in your software only when
it's in the hands of a real user yeah MH
so in a way I want to know are there a
sort of you know class of bugs that can
only be found by actual users in the
field yeah I feel like the I kind of
touched on the this earlier with the um
fragmentation of devices that's one that
is is is particularly painful I I
remember when I started my career I like
to think of yeah the the phases of of of
bug remediation being uh before in hands
of your customers and after and it used
to be this this big phase in between
where it was human powerered QA so when
I started my career huge QA teams would
work for sometimes months on QA your
going through a QA script and Qing your
software and the more that we've got to
lean agile rapid iteration and you know
being able to hot fix and patch things
and compon izing your software we can
ship faster and so that doesn't work
anymore you cannot have cannot have a
team of humans do two months of QA right
so from the left hand side of software
development that's kind of been replaced
with
this I think it's Capital One called
this team quality engineering which I
really love as a term but it's basically
saying look let's not have people going
through Word document scripts and
clicking around on the application and
typing in weird characters let's try and
automate that as much as possible and
then from the right hand side you you
have datadriven instrumentation with
products like bug snack that will tell
you yes this is a problem this is how
many customers is affected this is how
you go and fix it but what's funny is
and I always say I said this earlier
that we if everyone if you could get
that perfect vision from the left hand
side and get everything fixed we our
company wouldn't exist and our business
wouldn't exist so thankfully bugs exist
in the hands of customers but yeah I I
think that the ones that end up
happening in the hands of customers tend
to be where the data representing that
user has got into a strange state so I
think typically when you when you think
about pre-production and and pre-
customer testing you've got this like
unit test and integration tests you've
got these like clean room environments
where you start from the memory in your
application being completely blank then
you start up the application then you
you click around and do X Y and Z things
and in reality customers have quite a
dirty environment they're running in
because you need to do things like Save
State and make sure that you're caching
things and making sure that you're
authenticating the customer and so you
don't start off in this clean room
environment that you do in in
integration and unit test most of the
time so I think that most of the bugs I
see that happen are not due to
necessarily code paths being missed
because in theory you should have
good code coverage in your testing right
it's about weird data structures and
weird unclean data coming through I mean
we had uh at one of my previous
companies we had a bug that was caused
by uh a corrupted cookie format um in a
migration between two types of
authentication token there was a bug in
that migration and it caused certain a
large percentage of customers to have a
bad authentication token and when the
application was trying to read in that
data it would just kind of blow up
because it would it was expecting that
it could to be called or or something
like that and it was all corrupted and
so you're not going to think about that
when right oh that's a really that's a
really good that's a really good another
example there bad like data and caching
data that has gone into a layered state
but also um I think uh anything where
your migrating data as well because my
it's the same problem but migrating data
when you're running your tests you
expect the inputs to look like a certain
way but if the inputs uh uh look
different hopefully your migration will
fail cleanly but if it doesn't it's
going to migrate bad data into worse
data and so that that's I think the I've
said the word data about a million times
there but I think that's that's what the
the gets the problems that happen in the
hands of your customers is where you're
not operating that clean room
environment and there's caching and
authentication and cookies and local
storage and all sorts of stuff that's
stored on the device and is probably not
in the format you ECT there's other
things as well which are I think I
mentioned device fragmentation yeah one
of the exactly one of the fun funnest
examples of that is I forget um which
vendor it was so I won't name and shame
but um a mobile Android um phone
manufacturer one thing that a lot of
people don't know about um Android is
that yes there's this beautiful a AOSP
Android open source project but every
single vendor Forks it and messes around
with it and you see that from the user
interfaces but but actually that forking
and messing around with the code happens
at much lower levels and a major mobile
phone vendor uh in their modification of
um of the Android open source project
modified Json paring and again we're
back to Json again it's just because
everyone's using that as a interchange
format but they they literally modified
the J you know in Java you've got what
java. you. Json or whatever it is for
modifying and and reading and writing
Json they modified that so if you
expecting it in your test environments
for it to deserialize Json in a
particular way in one rare case it would
not deserialized data in the way that
every other Android device in the world
would and so look you can have maybe you
got lucky and had like let's say it was
HTC right maybe you had an HTC phone and
you would have CAU it or you run a
device farm and you tested it but if you
didn't then you have to wait for your
customers to tell you that because it
only happened in that particular
environment so yeah it's it's it's the
wild west especially on client side it's
you don't know what's happening with the
environment you do not control the
environments right you can't really
control but that also brings me up to
the question like you know I guess this
is more like a I mean just your thoughts
on it not to put you on the spot but uh
is it okay to delegate uh finding bugs
to our clients who paid money for our
software yeah people people I I don't
think it's okay I I think it's there's a
phrase that people use a lot and I
really hate it which is called test in
production I don't know if you've heard
people talking about test in production
and embracing Tes in production I I
think that's the wrong way of thinking
about things I think that either you are
very intentional about tradeoffs to mean
that maybe bugs will happen or you have
to be like well that sometimes bugs are
going to happen but we want to use
tooling and Technology to remediate them
as quick as possible and so yeah I
remember when I was talking about QA
earlier when I started my career the QA
Engineers the QA um team at one of my
companies I worked at would go through
scripts and they would do things that
you know that you'd fail the QA scripts
if some you know if you if your username
was 20,000 characters long or something
ridiculous and you're like these days
I'm like who cares like if a customer is
typing in a 20,000 character username
are they really a customer that we care
about that much like does it really
matter and it is it's it's so it's such
a brutal way of describing it but I
think that QA ranks mostly maybe you
have a P1 P2 P3 priority system but it's
very blunt about how it categorizes and
prioritizes bugs if you are measuring at
the bare minimum if you're aggregating
bugs by R cause then you can at least
say this bug is affecting 100 people and
say ah we've got to fix that straight
away so I see this as a way to better
allocate your resources effectively so
if you got a small engineering team use
that information to quickly get in and
fix that bug and it and and which bugs
matter the most varies by by companies
I've given a really basic example of how
many times it's happened but um the way
that we've built bug snag we allow you
to attach metadata diagnostic data to
any crash report and some key use cases
for that are look show me bugs that are
affect
key customers people who are spending
more than a million dollars a year with
us if if you're a B2B company or a big
company or show me bugs that are
happening in a really important flow
like uh login or payments flows or
whatever they are because if you do have
those scarce resources like every
engineering team development team does
you probably want to fix the bugs that
matter the most first and maybe if
people are typing in 20,000 character
usernames in a settings page you can
leave that one you can put that in the
in in the backlog in J for a
while okay okay interesting yeah it
makes perfect sense you rather you know
Focus your energy on the paying
customers as well yeah uh like the big
clients the big ticket yeah yeah oh all
the one all the all the all the the
highest pain as well like if you are a
if you're a consumer mobile application
that doesn't have like people spending a
lot of money you probably want to focus
your time on the bugs that are affecting
the highest volume of customers as well
whatever metric you want use in your
software just be thoughtful about it and
use data to drive it and then I think
you you can deliver software that's just
as stable as if you did a two-month QA
process and in fact improve it quicker
and get features to Market quicker right
okay I guess be I'd like to revisit that
a little bit later in the show um but
you know uh I I have this question also
about you know we talked a little bit
about uh you know you just briefly
touched you talked about this U you know
resources um that apps use for example
if you're having mobile apps there are
uh so we had an episode on um mobile
usability um a few weeks back with Matt
Lei and he had this uh you know he
talked about six principles of usability
and one of the principles was like
resources and how apps use resources and
uh he said there are certain apps which
actually lose out you know because the
way the manage resources for example
you're using something your phone really
heats up or you know batteries like you
know discharging like crazy do you have
any like you know I'm just just curious
do you have any examples of where you
might have seen you know because of this
kind of problem where the apps were not
really good in actually managing their
resources on the mobile phone then they
actually lost out you know to the market
share and then people just like started
you know uninstalling that app and yeah
I know I'm not going to use it yeah
there's a there's a classic example of
this okay it's it's a a class of
examples I think but um before I before
I go into that I think there's something
interesting in in the web services World
okay people talk about reliability and
you'll hear like job titles like site
reliability engineering and reliability
it's it's if you go and read the I love
it the Google SRE book is great I
actually think it's it's very well
written if you look at what the
definition typically of reliability is
it's kind of three layers and I think of
it it's like a pyramid right so
availability are my servers and services
even running H stability which is mainly
what bug snag focuses on and then
performance on the top right and if any
of these are are under are not working
correctly and not hitting your slas that
you've defined you're going to deliver a
poor customer experience right and the
the one you're talking about here I
think is mostly on the performance side
of things effectively right but actually
a lot of the times these performance
issues do end to end up in stability
issues so so there's this really classic
example and I think that there's plenty
of great thirdparty open source
libraries now to help you not make this
mistake but when I first started off in
my mobile Development Career at the when
mobile development wasn't really was
brand new uh on Smartphones at least
yeah almost every app that was being
built yeah if it had content in it you
would do the infinite scroll model right
so you load some data from an API and
then show it on the screen and then as
the user kept on scrolling so imagine
Instagram you're scrolling through all
your pictures on Instagram yeah now one
of the classic problems that happen in
these infinite content infinite scroll
environments was you You're great at
pulling in data from the API you're
great at allocating memory for that or
maybe Java does it for you automatically
or whatever yeah you're great at
rendering on the screen yeah but what
happens when it goes off the screen and
so there were so many apps in early in
early mobile development that didn't
think about the resource allocation
right of offscreen items and offscreen
things on on on on the menu and this is
true actually with web apps as well with
things react you want to make sure that
you're rendering things that are in the
viewports yes yes but anyway on mobile
if you're if you're Instagram and you're
downloading images that are you know
half a megabyte to four megabytes in
size and you're on a mobile device that
has hardly any Ram you need to really be
good at this and so you ended up having
this anyone who had a Android phone in
2009 or 2010 would be able to really
understand what I'm talking about here
Android used to feel like you were going
at three frames per second right it used
to feel like you were in a a stop motion
Movie and it was because the core
operating system wasn't super performant
for things like scrolling and they
thankfully fixed that but also because
there were no really clean patterns or
libraries or sdks for helping you manage
resources when they went off screen and
so yeah it's
uh I'm having having flashbacks a little
bit to that because it's so awful that
you know it was not the experience you
wanted on a on a buttery smooth mobile
like you had an iPhone and an Android
next to each other and one of them was a
beautiful buttery smooth experience and
the other one was a jerky experience
that ended up crashing because he had an
out of memory eror when all of these
images were in in memory right right
right yeah so I guess so so now that
we've you know sort of looked at all of
this I think you know towards the end
like we're sort of going towards like
you know my final part of the show and
uh I guess um I want to spend some time
on how we should deal with uh buggy
software so I guess you you have like
sort of touched upon it through our talk
but if I were to like sort of summarize
it one of the things that you know we're
talking about is like for example we
talked even about this Google Sri book
there's this thing that they have that
error budget right where they say that
if you don't hit that error budget then
you know maybe you shouldn't be spending
so much time on all all of these
different testing and things that you're
doing and then you know work on features
should should teams be actually doing
that or that's number one the second
thing is should we actually if that is
what we chose should we like sort of
double down on our QA effort if you have
an error budget and the third thing is
do you just like like you say in the
beginning just you know live with bugs
and maybe just have a sort of uh you
know Tri it rank it and then based on
the ranking you try to fix based on
whatever criteria you've chosen what are
the in your mind like the top couple of
things that teams should be doing or
companies should be doing actually yeah
I I think actually your flow that you've
laid out there is is a really sensible
framework for this I think that you need
to you need to measure right uh you need
to then Benchmark and have rules of
engagement for what happens if you're
not hitting your slas slos I'll talk
more about that in a second right and
then you need to have the the the the
the process and the people need to buy
into the process as well so let's start
right back at the measuring point of VI
so as you said in in web services web
applications in SRE land error budgets
which typically means you know the
number of 500 errors or 5x errors that
you're seeing um is a really good metric
of that now what we've done at bug snag
is we've extended that concept to any
application so we have this concept of
what we call a stability score and so
once you've installed bugsnag you drop
in our SDK we'll detect any unhanded
exception uh signal out of memory error
Android not responding application
freeze whatever it is is anything that
causes your session your customer to end
in a failed session will detect that
scenario and then because we know how
many sessions there were we've counted
the sessions as well we've got a
fraction we can say you know out of it's
like an era budget same thing out of um
uh a 100 sessions 99% of them were
Problem free and so out of that you get
a nice percentage you say Okay 99% of my
sessions were were good my stability
score is
99% but you can't can't just start there
you can't just have have that be like
okay great you need to do something
about it if it changes so the next thing
I think you need to do is decide on what
an acceptable range of uh stability
scores is what error budgets are okay
and we take the approach in bug snag
same as in the SR Google SRE book of
allowing our customers to select not
just uh one goal one target but actually
two we have an SLA goal and an SLO goal
goals the service level agreement goal
is look if your stability score drops
below this number then treat the world
as on fire you stop everything you drop
everything you're doing and you come and
get that stability uh up to the area it
needs to be in for example if Facebook's
uh API Returns the wrong data format you
need to figure out how to get your
application booing again right but
typically most people will be above that
SLA and then the next goal is an SLO a
service objective now serice service
level objective the way we see it we
call it a stability Target your target
stability is more aspirational it's more
like okay look what are our peers in the
market doing for this and uh where do we
want to get over time and so The Sweet
Spot then is in theory if you set those
slas and slos correctly is to be
somewhere in between the two and The
Sweet Spot is to have those lines get
closer and closer together over time as
you get more understanding about the the
quality of your application right and so
setting those slas and slos is not
something you just do as an engineering
team you need to talk to your business
counterparts or product team
counterparts and once you've done that
you end up with this really great
symbiotic relationship forming between
the product team and the and the
engineering team where I'll give you a
great example one of our customers uh in
the hospitality space uh they were
launching a premium hotels feature and
during the launch of that premium hotels
feature they Dro below their um critical
stability and uh so they actually
discussed they they told me they
discussed in a board meeting uh that hey
board of directors I know you're excited
about this premium premium hotels
feature but we're not going to ship it
on time and this is why and it wasn't
the engineering team saying that it was
the product team saying that so you've
got this like Buy in between the two
parts of the the R&D department for lack
of a better word of of like we agree
that this is going to be a negative
customer experience if we drop below
this number and so this is what we'll do
so that is really important that what do
you do about it is the kind of the final
piece of the puzzle I think as as you
alluded to if you've got targets you've
agreed upon you you're measuring you
have targets that you you're you're
agreed upon with the product team what
do you do about it next well there's a
bunch of approaches here um the old way
to do things like with QA would be to
toss problems over the fence and some
companies do this and that's fine what I
mean by this is having a team of
Developers ERS that just fix bugs now I
don't know how many developers you've
met that are super excited about
spending all their day fixing bugs they
definitely exist I have met them before
I have met okay please introduce me to
them it's not the nor it's not every
developer for sure yeah you know I I
think that builds the wrong this is
subjective this is my opinion now but I
think that builds the wrong attitude in
an engineering team I think that what
you're seeing Trends wise more and more
is that the code that you write as a
software engineer you own for a long
time you don't just build it and it's
like back in the day you used to when
you shipped Microsoft Office uh they
print it on a CD and you'd ship it to
Best Buy and someone would buy it from
the store like that's not how it works
anymore you've written code you're GNA
see that code again probably tomorrow uh
and so having ownership after things go
to production I think is a critical
mindset for software developers it
should be obvious I think to a lot of
listeners but I think it's a critical
mindset to have and so having another
team that fixes bugs I think is a bad
idea right one in terms of actual
positive approaches I've seen two that
work really well one of them is
ownership based on who touched the code
last so if you see a bug a bug comes
into production it's been prioritized
based on using bug snags rankings or
whatever you're using or someone in jir
has ranked it up to the right level then
ideally the person who touch that code
last is going to be the expert in that
area now that's not always so
straightforward because it might be that
someone did a commit that changed all
tabs to spaces in the entire code base
and now their names all over the whole
the whole code base but um if you use
git blame it will tell you who last
touched the code and maybe that's a good
way to assign things now a better way of
doing it that is less granular is what
team owns this codebase now uh a lot of
teams are migrating to using github's
Code owners file format I'm not sure if
you've seen this but you can Define now
in a file um in your repo this is who
owns this part of the code base so it's
less finger pointy then it's not like oh
James changed tabs to spaces and now he
made this bug uh it's more this team is
responsible for this area so I think
that's a really good approach an
alternative approach if you haven't yet
adopted those techniques is is to do uh
I think Airbnb call it bug Sheriff uh or
we used to call it bug Warrior uh my
previous company and the idea is that
you're on rotation so you and probably a
buddy an engineering buddy uh are going
to be responsible for triaging
prioritizing and fixing bugs on a rot
rotating basis and really this shouldn't
be too frequently you you should set up
the rotation such that the B you're only
bug Warrior one out of every five six
weeks at the at the shortest time period
but the idea here is that you hopefully
it might not be code that you've written
but it does give you empathy for other
parts of the code base so it still gives
you empathy and ownership around the
software that you're delivering to your
customers so it really depends on how
sophisticated you want to be but I think
you can't actually triage and fix bugs
effectively unless you commit to a
process for doing so and they're two
really good techniques I like for for
doing that right so so I guess to sort
of summarize first uh you know obviously
you you set up like benchmarks um
measure it look at the data and then you
know Rank by however either you're using
your software or or whatever your
favorite thing or somebody goes in and
ranks it and then of course then the
part about who actually goes and fixes
it instead of blaming it you know sort
of assign it to team me to an to an
entire team and you know do like various
approaches like you said I like this bug
Warrior uh so that kind of thing and
then uh go and fix the bugs so and also
and like one important thing is the
person uh like the team who wrote the
code should be the ones who fix it so
don't like toss it over I think I think
that that's pretty much what a lot of
companies are doing but yeah it's good
to sort of reiterate that uh through
this well I I tell you what I the one
thing to definitely not do is to wait
for customers to complain and I think
that no matter if you're using bug snag
and you've got a bug Warrior and if
you've got great jur triage or whatever
you're doing right like be data driven
it's not that hard to adopt a dat data
driven approach to uh prioritizing and
fixing uh and remediating bugs so like
yes there's great tools out there that
but but even if you want to build your
own stuff or make your own algorithms or
rank them your own way don't wait for
customers to complain because by the
time customers to complain probably 50
other customers have already left your
products so that's the thing that I
still see a lot of teams doing and it
scares me when I see
that okay this is great Jam I think I I
think that probably um all I um have I I
guess I I would just before I end I
think I just I was wondering if you
could again tell me a little bit about
that stability score because that's one
thing that I uh is that how how do you
how do you do that could you just like
sort of reiterate because that was
really that PE my interest so can we
just like go over okay yeah yeah yeah
yeah so so effectively we want to help
people understand what percentage of of
user interactions with your product
succeeded or failed and to to break it
down a little bit more specifically
let's say you're in a JavaScript
application a react application right um
we will detect if there are unhandled
exceptions we'll detect if there
unhandled promise rejections or we'll
detect if there's an exception that was
in an a callback like I was talking
about earlier if any of those situations
happen or in in if you're using a react
a framework like react but also detect
errors that bubble up to a react error
boundary and so depending on the
platform We have basically built these
hooks to hook into failure States in
your product okay um so sure these are
still going to cause your customers to
have a bad experience our product
doesn't magically uh stop bugs from
happening but it will detect when they
happen and then that all feeds into the
stability score so if your session had
any of those scenarios happen that
counts as a failed session and it's
different techniques on different
platforms but it's always the same
underlying concept I want to know which
customers had a positive experience what
percentage of that customer base so
that's how we calculate it we've got a
we've got an article on our blog about
this as well that that talks about it a
bit more in depth okay it's really
interesting so uh again yeah I think
this is a great conversation so thanks
James I think uh this probably ends our
a session but you know if uh listeners
want to uh you know reach out to you is
there um you know a Twitter handle that
they can you know reach out to uh would
you like to yeah I'm I'm not Super
Active on Twitter but I do check my
messages I'm I'm at loopj l o PJ okay um
and I'm also on Lin as well you can find
me I'm I'm James James Smith is a very
common name but if you type James Smith
bug snag into LinkedIn you'll find me
pretty quickly okay and also um bug
snag.com is is our website as well and
you can I've got plenty of blog posts
and things on there as well okay okay
thank you very much and this is Priyanka
Ragan signing off for software
engineering radio thanks for
listening become an autonomous digital
Enterprise and your business can achieve
aame status in intelligent predictive
systems effortless Automation and
technology and people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
Enterprise visit bmc.com aame for more
information thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by it e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.com net to provide feedback you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook
Twitter or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for listening